<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Product Brief</title>
    <description>in which I discuss ideas to improve or next-step products, write about technical people writing, and ramble about life</description>
    <link>https://productbrief.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://productbrief.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 10:41:38 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 10:41:38 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.0</generator>

    
      <item>
        <title>Books That Have Taught Me Product Management</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr&lt;/em&gt;: I recently saw a LinkedIn post that asked for a list of books helpful for upping one’s game as a technical product manager. This post is the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-technical-product-management&quot;&gt;What is Technical Product Management?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think of it as the combo/intersection of product management and technical work, so books that help me sharpen either of those are really valuable to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a list of some of the books that have been most pivotal in my experience and have really helped me in my roles, especially as a PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not including anything technical in this post, because it’s gonna vary widely with what you’re interested in? APIs? Databases? JS libraries? Search algorithms? Google books about those things. But here’s a list of books about product management and related skills and ideas that have really influenced me. I may revisit and revise in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-negotiation-collaboration-and-management&quot;&gt;About negotiation, collaboration, and management&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Never-Split-Difference-Negotiating-Depended/dp/0062407805&quot;&gt;Never Split the Difference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Crucial-Conversations-Talking-Stakes-Second/dp/0071771328&quot;&gt;Crucial Conversations: Talking When the Stakes are High&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Team-Topologies-Organizing-Business-Technology/dp/1942788819&quot;&gt;Team Topologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Phoenix-Project-DevOps-Helping-Business/dp/1942788290&quot;&gt;The Phoenix Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Unicorn-Project-Developers-Disruption-Thriving/dp/1942788762&quot;&gt;The Unicorn Project&lt;/a&gt; - a followup to &lt;em&gt;The Phoenix Project&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Project-Management-Humans-Helping-People-ebook/dp/B0759QS26P&quot;&gt;Project Management for Humans: Helping People Get Things Done&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done-Stress-Free-Productivity/dp/0143126563&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done: The Art of Stress-Free Productivity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-product-management-as-such&quot;&gt;About product management as such&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Cracking-PM-Interview-Product-Technology-ebook/dp/B00ISYMUR6&quot;&gt;Cracking the PM Interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/INSPIRED-Create-Tech-Products-Customers-ebook/dp/B077NRB36N&quot;&gt;Inspired: Create Tech Products that Customers Love&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Product-Roadmaps-Relaunched-Direction-Uncertainty-ebook/dp/B076VX53K1&quot;&gt;Product Roadmaps Relaunched&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-business-and-careers-in-software-development&quot;&gt;About business and careers in software development&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Lean-Startup-Entrepreneurs-Continuous-Innovation/dp/0307887898&quot;&gt;The Lean Startup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Unlocking-Customer-Value-Chain-Decoupling/dp/152476308X&quot;&gt;Unlocking the Customer Value Chain: How Decoupling Drives Consumer Disruption&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/First-90-Days-Strategies-Expanded/dp/1422188612&quot;&gt;The First 90 Days: Proven Strategies for Getting Up to Speed Faster and Smarter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Managing-Up-Move-Work-Succeed/dp/1119436680&quot;&gt;Managing Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Managing-Oneself-Harvard-Business-Classics/dp/142212312X&quot;&gt;Managing Oneself&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/general-ideas/soft-skills/2020/06/01/books-that-have-taught-me-product-management.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/general-ideas/soft-skills/2020/06/01/books-that-have-taught-me-product-management.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>general-ideas</category>
        
        <category>soft-skills</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What I've Been Learning Piecemeal</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr&lt;/em&gt;: I’ve been lengthening the legs of my skills “tripod” - and done piecemeal, it’s been fun and easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great mentor of mine, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/oliviermeyer/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Olivier Meyer&lt;/a&gt;, told me one time that in his mind, product management is like a stool resting on a trio of legs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organization skills and knowledge - things like running a meeting well, planning and revising plans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;business and human skills and knowledge - things like communicating the correct information clearly to the appropriate audience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;technical skills and knowledge - the subject matter of your product&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think he was right. Furthermore, I think these three legs apply to all professionals, albeit in proportions that vary with your roles and goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, when we start a new role, we have a base set of skills and experience around it, but want - need - to keep growing those skills. That was certain the case for me. I came into product management gradually from technical writing and API documentation. I’m naturally a people person, concerned with others’ opinions and feelings, and I take real pains to express myself clearly and help others express themselves clearly when they seem to be struggling with it. As I’ve gotten older, and with good mentorship, I think I’ve gotten more discreet. That is, I’ve gotten better at knowing what to say and to whom… or what not to say. Great. So I have a base set of people skills, management skills, and tech skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, a while ago, I set upon a program of actively growing my skills. My temperament is decidedly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bent toward taking classes and earning degrees. So instead, I’ve been doing things piecemeal - as I want, when I want, based on my interests and needs. In the last few years, here’s how I’ve been turning myself toward upping my three product management legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;organizational-skills-and-knowledge&quot;&gt;Organizational Skills and Knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of books and seeking lots of mentorship. Most recently, my manager, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/leoalfo/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Leonor Alfonso&lt;/a&gt;, has been amazing at patiently helping my grow in this area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But other times, I have particular questions or find myself shouting in my head, and need a way of resolving these without going to someone else. Lately, for instance, I needed to produce a roadmap for further into the future than I felt I could really predict. “What do I do!?!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done-Stress-Free-Productivity/dp/0143126563&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done: The Art of Stress-Free Productivity&lt;/a&gt; by David Allen is a great manual for keeping tasks organized and moving along &lt;em&gt;without stressing over it all&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Brett Harned’s overview work &lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Project-Management-Humans-Helping-People/dp/1933820519/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Project Management for Humans: Helping People Get Things Done&lt;/a&gt; is great for helping you get your bearings when your job is running complicated or multi-person projects.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Todd Lombardo’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Product-Roadmaps-Relaunched-Direction-Uncertainty/dp/149197172X&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Product Roadmaps Relaunched: How to Set Direction while Embracing Uncertainty&lt;/a&gt; is a must-read for making roadmaps not lie and generally suck.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;business-and-human-skills-and-knowledge&quot;&gt;Business and Human Skills and Knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books and mentors: this is a theme for me with learning soft skills. The number one thing for learning soft skills is not being ashamed of not knowing having them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve sought mentors to my great benefit. Bosses can be great mentors. They are human, so we can’t expect them to know everything, but I have found that finding out what they know and learning from them is very fruitful. The aforementioned Olivier Meyer and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/scotthurrey/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Scott Hurrey&lt;/a&gt; have both been very helpful for me in this regard.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Crucial-Conversations-Talking-Stakes-Second/dp/0071775307/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Crucial Conversations: Tools for Talking When Stakes Are High, Second Edition&lt;/a&gt;, by Patterson, Grenny, McMillan, and Switzler, is a fantastic book. It’s not about how to win conversations, but about how to have them when they’re hard. It’s especially good for helping me not only keep my cool but for helping me help my conversation partners keep cool.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Never-Split-Difference-Negotiating-Depended/dp/0062407805/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Never Split the Difference: Negotiating As If Your Life Depended On It&lt;/a&gt;, Chris Voss and Tahl Raz, is amazing. Life-altering. It saved me 50% on the cost of roof repairs in my first week and has gone on to help me manage upward, manage downward, and build consensus with clients and coworkers alike.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-skills-and-knowledge&quot;&gt;Technical Skills and Knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My product management work isn’t especially technical. I work on a product that deals with non-technical subject matter and faces end-users who aren’t technical people. It’s also been more than a few years since I was a computer science minor. While the theories I learned have never left me, the core skills involved in programming have definitely progressed. And while my goal is not to be an engineer, well, the more you know, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dev forums&lt;/strong&gt;: We all know about stackoverflow. But the last few years, I’ve done a lot of lurking on &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dev.to&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a great site.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code challenges&lt;/strong&gt;: Lately, I’ve started doing some of dev.to’s coding challenges, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://dev.to/thepracticaldev/daily-challenge-158-rgb-to-hex-conversion-559n&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;make a function to convert rgb to hex&lt;/a&gt;. Here are &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/ryanhaber/b3a45b57348b3c3e49f9acbfe625545d&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;my results of that one&lt;/a&gt;. Nothing complicated, but fun. And in this one, I learned that python has string interpolation very much like my good old friend C.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;script src=&quot;https://gist.github.com/ryanhaber/b3a45b57348b3c3e49f9acbfe625545d.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Teaching others&lt;/strong&gt;: My HTML and CSS skills are sharp and my Javascript skill level is adequate for my needs. I find myself helping people who want to tweak their blogs or build personal websites or portfolios without using a code-free builder. But my favorite protegee is my niece. She’s 12 and learning to code. After mastering &lt;a href=&quot;https://scratch.mit.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;scratch&lt;/a&gt; a visual coding platform for kids, she wanted to cut her teeth into something more significant. So I’m working through a book (&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Creative-Coding-Python-Programming-Projects/dp/1631595814&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Creative Coding in Python: 30+ Programming Projects in Art, Games, and More&lt;/a&gt;) with her. She’s loving it and so am I. While I know what a variable is, I have found myself learning little bits here and there, filling in gaps in my piecemeal learning. If you’re an engineer and your protegee is a college student, this book is not right for you. But mentoring and teaching are right for everyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-takeaway&quot;&gt;The Takeaway&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The takeaway here is simple. Whether you’re a product manager, a UX designer, a tech writer, a dev, or even a recruiter - you’re going to benefit from building organization skills, human skills, and technical skills. A recruiter doesn’t have to be a dev or know all the dev skills, but it’s good for recruiters to learn the distinction between Java and Javascript; a dev doesn’t necessarily have to manage a fleet of people, but it will only help her career to know how to keep a large project organized. And the good news is that you can learn these things piecemeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@flysi3000?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Simon Abrams&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/s/photos/man-coding?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/career/memoirs/coding/learning/2020/01/20/pm-learns-piecemeal.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/career/memoirs/coding/learning/2020/01/20/pm-learns-piecemeal.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>career</category>
        
        <category>memoirs</category>
        
        <category>coding</category>
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Docs and Why</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr&lt;/em&gt;: Nothing is worse than having to write docs - except not having them when you need them. You want not too little, but not too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-bother&quot;&gt;Why Bother?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Docs-writing sucks. That’s why you don’t want to do it, right? Well, that’s fair enough. And even in a world where we rightly prefer working code over documenting the everloving f*@k out of things, there are some good reasons to document your work - whether as code or as an end-product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;You are helping yourself.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;The better your documentation is, the fewer questions people will ask you in the future. And when they ask you questions, you will be able to send them a link instead of writing documentation. Based on this reasoning, it is a good idea &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to document things that nobody will ever care about. You might be surprised that somebody asks about X. If that happens, answer their question and add your answer to the documentation in a place where people can find it. Also, you might have to revisit something six months or a year later. It will help you if you made good docs while you were working on it the first time.&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;You are helping your future self.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;You will one day arrive at a new job or join a new team. You will hope that the people there have written good docs to help you get started. Pay it forward by writing good docs for whoever comes after you.&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;You are helping your team.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;You might win the lottery one day and leave suddenly. Your team will love you if it make it easy for them by documenting your work well.&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;strong&gt;You are helping our clients or customers.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;br /&gt;When our stuff is easy to use, people use it more. If it is not easy to use, we can at least explain it and make it feel easy. When we do these things, we get more sales and more renewals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-makes-good-documentation&quot;&gt;What Makes Good Documentation?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quantifying-the-value-and-quality-of-documentation&quot;&gt;Quantifying the Value and Quality of Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often think that the value of docs is subjective or unquantifiable. This is rarely the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of writing is that it can be written once and shared many times, whereas in-person or real-time forms of communication need to be repeated each time a new person needs the information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is money. Wasted time is wasted money and lost productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I answer a question for the external developer community and it takes me 10 minutes, and at my pay scale that is, to keep things easy, say $10, then the company pays $10 each time I answer that question. If the question comes in daily, then in the course of a working year of 240 days, the question costs the company $2400. If I write a good doc and make it easily findable at a cost of $60 one-time, I think you can see how the savings is dramatic. In my experience, a well-written, easily-findable answer eliminates the question 90% of the time. For the other 10%, you can smugly send a link and sit back while the past-you does the present-you’s job for you. This scenario is simplified, but it is a real-life scenario that I live repeatedly. We all answer any number of questions over and over again because of disorganized knowledge management. This problem is not unique to our company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the complexity of your documentation problem and your channels for interacting with your docs’ users, you can gather just this sort of data and more. How long does it take to read a doc? How many times do people read the doc and then contact customer support? How often is a question asked of customer support? How easy is it to find the document in the docs repository when you know it exists? How often do internal or external search queries for relevant questions bring up the relevant doc or an irrelevant doc? What is the user behavior like when they land on a doc from a seemingly relevant search query. All of this questions can be answered objectively using modern technology. These answers, in turn, are the first data points for understanding the cost of difficult or missing documentation. They are a good first step in figuring out what needs to be documented or what docs need improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is, then, what things should be documented?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Document questions that are clearly or probably going to be asked.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When you get asked a new question, might as well write it in a generally-applicable way if possible and quickly insert it into the best location in your documentation structure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What should not be documented?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Things nobody cares about&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Things that you are proud of but really only you care about, like how hard you worked - tell your mom or write a blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The trick is to anticipate the probable audiences for a subject matter and what they probably need to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much for the value of a doc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the quality of a doc? Isn’t this subjective?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Not at all. A doc has a job to do and it is good inasmuch as it accomplishes that task. That is the absolute and completely objective standard to the quality of technical documentation. Suppose I write a document for experienced Java engineers and, out of a 100 engineers, 17 understand it. No matter how smart I think I am, I have failed. That score will save very few people any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other objective standards, too. The subject of readability, the ease and speed with which prose can be read and understood, is a very well researched topic. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://readable.io&quot;&gt;https://readable.io&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://hemingwayapp.com&quot;&gt;https://hemingwayapp.com&lt;/a&gt; for free or low-cost readability scorers that will tell you the difficulty or ease of reading your doc and what makes it easier or harder. They typically use a set of established formulas to return a grade level, a letter grade, or a percentage score. They often give good tips for improving your particular text. Aim for a 7-9th grade reading level. This isn’t dumbing anything down - this is making it so your document’s user does not have to figure out what you were trying to say. This is just making yourself plain to even a teenager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principles and tips below will help you take your “business-ese” and easily transform it into clear text that your intended audience can understand. One caveat is that big words affect readability. Some words, like &lt;em&gt;utilize&lt;/em&gt; should almost always be replaced with &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; because they mean the same thing and use is easier. Other times, you just have to use a bigger word like &lt;em&gt;reciprocation&lt;/em&gt;. That’s OK. Just be readable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-your-audience&quot;&gt;Understand Your Audience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good documentation is written for a specific audience. The author understands the audience and writes only those things that the audience needs to know. The author explains those things in a way that the audience can understand. Some examples include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other engineers / your future self&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Educated, intelligent non-engineers: PMs, Designers, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Managers, Directors, or Executives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;External developers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Marketing or sales team members&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;External end-users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understand-your-audiences-needs&quot;&gt;Understand Your Audience’s Needs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audiences need different things at different times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conceptual&lt;/strong&gt;: Theoretical overview that explains the &lt;em&gt;What?&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Why?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutorial&lt;/strong&gt;: How-to steps that explain &lt;em&gt;How&lt;/em&gt; to accomplish a task.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reference&lt;/strong&gt;: Look-up material when your audience needs to know a fact, like a definition of a word or the parameters accepted by a method.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-a-matrix-of-needs&quot;&gt;Make a Matrix of Needs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have made a grid of audiences and their potential needs, you can make rational decisions about which ones to document. For example, consider the subject of something technical like a data pipeline. In the follow matrix of needs, we mark spaces with X if we think we probably do not need to write the document because the audience does not likely need it. Otherwise, we comment on what the document should accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
  table, th, tr, td {
    border: 1px solid black;
    padding: 5px;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;wrapped&quot;&gt;
  &lt;colgroup&gt;
    &lt;col /&gt;
    &lt;col /&gt;
    &lt;col /&gt;
    &lt;col /&gt;
  &lt;/colgroup&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Audience&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Conceptual&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Tutorial&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Reference&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Other engineers&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Explain to other engineers what the pipeline does, how it works, and why we set it up that way, so they can get started working on the pipeline. Engineers looking at your code need to know: (a) what you did and (b) why you did it that way. (A) should be clear from the code itself. Comments can help explain (B). &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Help engineers set up their environment.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;List of classes and methods.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;PMs / POs&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Explain to PMs / POs in a simple way &lt;span&gt;what the pipeline does, how it works, and why we set it up that way.&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;X&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;List of unusual words and their meanings in the context.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td colspan=&quot;1&quot;&gt;Executive summary&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td colspan=&quot;1&quot;&gt;Explain in simple, common words, very briefly, what the pipeline does and why.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td colspan=&quot;1&quot;&gt;X&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td colspan=&quot;1&quot;&gt;X&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;universal-principles&quot;&gt;Universal Principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;concise&quot;&gt;Concise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not use more words than you have to. If a sentence can have 10 words and you write 13 words, you have written 30% more than you need to. You ask your reader to read 30% more than they need to. Your writing feels fluffier the more you do this. If you do it a lot, it becomes harder to find answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pro tip: Avoid using adjectives. Adjectives are usually unnecessary and often change. If you write, “The blue button,” a UX designer will come along and change the color and your docs will be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Example:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went up to the store in order to buy some organic eggs.  = 13 words&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went &lt;del&gt;up&lt;/del&gt; to the store &lt;del&gt;in order&lt;/del&gt; to buy &lt;del&gt;some organic&lt;/del&gt; eggs.  → Remove words that do not add value for the particular audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to the store to buy eggs. = 8 words = 38% savings.  → Multiply this savings across 100 pages of documentation. &amp;amp;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;complete&quot;&gt;Complete&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to include everything that somebody is likely to want to know. Do not include things that will not help other people with their work. If you are really proud of something, show it to your mother. The rest of us will be proud of you when we can read your docs and appreciate your work without have to read all the stuff you are proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro tip&lt;/strong&gt;: Do not create the same content twice if you can avoid it. Instead, use links and iframes to connect or display content as needed. Put related pieces of content close to each other. If related content cannot go nearby, connect them using links, iframes, or another such tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clear&quot;&gt;Clear&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clarity is objective.&lt;/strong&gt; If your intended audience does not understand your docs, your docs are not clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro tips&lt;/strong&gt;: use a readability checker like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.readable.io&quot;&gt;https://www.readable.io&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hemingwayapp.com&quot;&gt;https://www.hemingwayapp.com&lt;/a&gt; to help you achieve the right level for your writing. For technical documentation, aim for levels 7-9. If the only “problem” with your writing is that you have a number of large words that are necessary in the context, that’s OK. You might have to use words like &lt;em&gt;application&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;analytical&lt;/em&gt; that typically make a doc a bit harder. You do &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; have to use words like &lt;em&gt;utilize&lt;/em&gt; when a word like &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; is just as good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;correct&quot;&gt;Correct&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get someone else who understands your content to sanity check it for correctness. If your document is found by a reader to be inaccurate, they will wonder why they should read your work anymore. In some situations, inaccurate information can cause serious harm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;organize-your-content&quot;&gt;Organize Your Content&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;general-principles&quot;&gt;General principles:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep related content close to each other.&lt;br /&gt;If a user only needs a bit of information in one place, then put that information in that place. If the user needs the information in more than one place, put it in one place and then link, iframe, or mention it in the other places.&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Example&lt;/b&gt;: &lt;em&gt;To log into your account you need credentials. For steps to get credentials, see Getting Credentials&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoid writing the same documentation twice.&lt;br /&gt;When someone updates one place, they will often forget to update the other. The two pieces of content fall out of sync and the documentation as a whole becomes less trustworthy.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make different kinds of content (conceptual, reference, etc) visually distinct. Separate them from each other when it makes sense.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use clear heading titles. Headings should answer a question. Headings for conceptual and reference content are usually nouns. Headings for tutorial (how-to) content should start with a verb. Generally, headers should not rely on knowledge that a person will not have before reading the content.&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Bad&lt;/b&gt;: &lt;em&gt;How Do I LMGTFY?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Good&lt;/b&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Using Let Me Google That For You&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Better&lt;/b&gt;: &lt;em&gt;Making Your Friends Feel Bad by Pointing Out How to Google&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bullet points vs numbered lists:&lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If order does not matter, for instance, when you describe best practices that are independent of each other or when you are sharing concrete facts, then use bullet points (unordered list).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If order does matter, for instance, when you list the steps of a procedure, use a numbered list (ordered list).&lt;br /&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a table of contents for a long document or for a collection of documents.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each thing should be about one thing. You should be able to summarize every book, chapter, paragraph, and procedure in a single sentence.&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use tags. Try to use existing tags instead of inventing new ones, whenever possible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;simple-tips-that-anyone-can-do&quot;&gt;Simple Tips That Anyone Can Do&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write simple text. Short sentences, easy words, active-voice verbs all help readers quickly move through text.
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put the documentation where it is relevant.&lt;br /&gt;If it is relevant to multiple things, make it a separate topic and link to it from all the places where it is relevant.
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use existing standards whenever they apply.
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use formatting consistently. Otherwise, the formatting loses meaning. Below are some common standards for documentation formatting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;common-standards-for-formatting-technical-documentation&quot;&gt;Common Standards for Formatting Technical Documentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boldface&lt;/strong&gt; - use boldface to highlight exact words as they appear in the UI when a user needs them for taking action. If they are not exact words or they are not needed for action at that moment, don’t use boldface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Monospace&lt;/code&gt; - use monospace to indicate words or string as an exact match in code or other technical sources like config files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Italic&lt;/em&gt; - use italic to indicate that words or string is an exact match that is not in code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ordered lists - use for steps or other information in which the order is essential&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unordered lists - use for information in which the order doesn’t matter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;H1 - top-level subjects, unless there is no special format for a title, in which case, use H1 for the title of a document&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/@neonbrand?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;NeONBRAND&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/search/photos/writing?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/general-ideas/soft-skills/2019/06/10/how-to-docs-and-why-copy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/general-ideas/soft-skills/2019/06/10/how-to-docs-and-why-copy.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>general-ideas</category>
        
        <category>soft-skills</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Soft Skills You Need</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr&lt;/em&gt;: There are great resources out there to help you learn to manage yourself and others, negotiate, network, and more. Use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-soft-skills&quot;&gt;Why Soft Skills&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a lot of talk about soft skills lately. It may be that we’ve emphasized understanding STEM subjects to the detriment of working with human subjects. If you google &lt;em&gt;most important soft skills&lt;/em&gt;, you come up with a lot of different lists. In my own life the following skills have made a measurable impact. Measurable, because as I have learned them, I have seen my career advance not only in responsibilities but also in dollars and cents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reverse is true. In my past I have made some “career limiting moves”. Now that I know better for the most part, I cringe when I see others do these things because they lack soft skills. Six months after telling the boss in public that his idea is dumb, the social cludge wonders why the boss didn’t put him up for a promotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans are humans. Learning to work and play with humans is pretty important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With each skill, I make a recommendation or two for reading or viewing. Of course, the best way to really improve is to talk out scenarios with mentors and smart peers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-skills&quot;&gt;The Skills&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;managing-oneself-ones-subordinates-and-ones-superiors&quot;&gt;Managing oneself, one’s subordinates, and one’s superiors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Managing-Oneself-Harvard-Business-Classics-ebook/dp/B00TXS49UW&quot;&gt;Managing Oneself&lt;/a&gt; This book is a classic and I can see why. It’s short and sweet and helped me to understand my study/work habits and needs, and to quickly understand those of the people around me. This understanding in turn has helped me to figure out how I can both be of service to them and also keep them from getting in my way 🙃.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;negotation&quot;&gt;Negotation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Never-Split-Difference-Negotiating-Depended-ebook/dp/B014DUR7L2&quot;&gt;Never Split the Difference&lt;/a&gt; This book has been nothing short of lifechanging for me. I needed repairs to my roof. The roofer gave me his estimate. And with one question, which I learned to formulate by reading this book, I got him to cut his price down from $900 to $450.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;networking-and-crossing-silos&quot;&gt;Networking and Crossing Silos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/How-Win-Friends-Influence-People-ebook/dp/B003WEAI4E/&quot;&gt;How to Win Friends and Influence People&lt;/a&gt; is a fairly wordy one, but is good nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Never-Eat-Alone-Expanded-Updated-ebook/dp/B00H6JBFOS/&quot;&gt;Never Eat Alone&lt;/a&gt; is well received, but I haven’t read it yet. If you read it, let me know how you like it below 👇.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;having-hard-conversations&quot;&gt;Having hard conversations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Crucial-Conversations-Talking-Stakes-Second-ebook/dp/B005K0AYH4/&quot;&gt;Crucial Conversations&lt;/a&gt; does not teach you how to win conversations, but rather how to have them when the subject matter is emotionally charged. It has &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; helped me learn to keep calm and help the others in the conversation also keep an even keel and hear each other out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-solving&quot;&gt;Problem solving&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Art-Strategy-Theorists-Success-Business-ebook/dp/B001FA0NOM/&quot;&gt;The Art of Strategy: A Game Theorist’s Guide to Success in Business and Life&lt;/a&gt; is a fantastic book. It doesn’t just outline strategies. Rather, it goes over, chapter by chapter, key principles and techniques that you can use to put together a strategy fitted to your situation, be it a board game or a career move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-management&quot;&gt;Time Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Getting-Things-Done-Stress-Free-Productivity-ebook/dp/B00KWG9M2E/&quot;&gt;Getting Things Done: The Art of Stress-Free Productivity&lt;/a&gt; was a real game changer for me. Since reading it, I’ve been able to engage in more projects and activities and feel less stressed than ever before. I don’t use his system fully, because make no mistake, it is a big, hulking system, but I use some of its core principles and I am very glad that I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;written-communication&quot;&gt;Written Communication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Complete-Plain-Words-Ernest-Gowers/dp/1567922031/&quot;&gt;The Complete Plain Words&lt;/a&gt; is a classic of clear and productive writing. It is easy and has lots of examples. You probably won’t read it all in one sitting. Instead, read it in bites and let it sink in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;oral-communication&quot;&gt;Oral Communication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0684846470/&quot;&gt;How to Speak, How to Listen&lt;/a&gt; is a classic. I haven’t read it though, so let me know if you like it. :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0060987405/&quot;&gt;On Speaking Well&lt;/a&gt; by a former presidential speechwriter. I haven’t read the book yet, but this woman knows her stuff. I suspect a lot of the public speaking skills translate, with some tweaking, to small-group or one-on-one conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also highly recommend the YouTube series &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/charismaoncommand/videos&quot;&gt;Charisma On Command&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;one-stop-shop&quot;&gt;One Stop Shop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Soft-Skills-software-developers-manual/dp/1617292397&quot;&gt;Soft Skills: The software developer’s life manual&lt;/a&gt; is a good book. I haven’t read it all, but the parts that I read were really good. It covers a lot of the topics above and will be helpful not only for software developers, but for people who sometimes feel awkward. Or who don’t, but maybe should 😊.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;margin-top: 100px; font-size:.75em&quot;&gt;Photo by &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/sUXXO3xPBYo?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Rob Curran&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/search/photos/crowd?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/general-ideas/soft-skills/2019/05/18/soft-skills-you-need.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/general-ideas/soft-skills/2019/05/18/soft-skills-you-need.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>general-ideas</category>
        
        <category>soft-skills</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Anatomy of a Good Ticket</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr&lt;/em&gt;: A good ticket is clear, correct, complete, and concise. It uses straightforward grammar, includes background information to aid good decision-making, and sets clear expectations. A good ticket is neither too big nor too small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless you are a single developer writing code to solve your own, individual problem, the people who want the software are not the exact same set as those who make it. As a result, communication is necessary between the set of wanters and the set of makers. And the greater the size of the sets and the less they overlap, the more crucial it is to have clear written communication to avoid wasted effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The Solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work requirements usually get broken down into tickets. These tickets can be seen as atomic or, perhaps, as being small molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good tickets include background information.&lt;/strong&gt; This aids good decision-making by people who come after the original writer. It is often packaged as a &lt;strong&gt;user story&lt;/strong&gt;. A user story explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who will benefit or has a problem that needs to be solved&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the problem or the desired solution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the end goal of the beneficiary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format of a user story is usually something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a (kind of user), I want/need (solution to problem) so that I (experience or result obtained).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this information, the product development team of designers and engineers can start solving a problem, enabling them to take ownership of the problem and the customer’s pain. Most importantly, it’s formatted in a way that engages their skills and talents, which is why they were hired in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Four Cs of Good tickets are:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt; - They reflect what is actually wanted, precisely and accurately. The key to this is that the Product Manager (PM) or Product Owner (PO) must work with stakeholders and understand industry standards. In case of uncertainty, a good PM/PO works with a very knowledgeable subset of the product team to arrive at a precise and accurate definition.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;clear&lt;/strong&gt; - They are clear. I recommend running the description portion of tickets through a readability scanner like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hemingwayapp.com&quot;&gt;Hemingway App&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;complete&lt;/strong&gt; yet &lt;strong&gt;concise&lt;/strong&gt; - They contain everything the team needs to get started, otherwise they will have to waste time coming back for more information. While writing a ticket, you should cut unnecessary details, attachments, and even words or phrases; otherwise, the ticket quickly becomes a jungle, and key information will get lost in the clutter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a ticket lacks any of these four Cs, the team will waste time having to reconnect and sort through old notes trying to figure out what was meant and whether it still applies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good tickets use straightforward grammar.&lt;/strong&gt; This is part of clarity. It is also worth calling out specially. The point of writing a ticket is to make its contents understood. Lots of people unconsciously use unnecessarily long or complicated words and phrases. A common offense is to use words like &lt;em&gt;utilize&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt;. The cumulative effect of big words and long sentences is cluttered communication. Avoid jargon that your intended audience is unlikely to know. Every extra or unknown word increases the chance of a reader getting distracted or giving up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run your writing through a readability scanner to see where you can make improvements. Aim for writing at the 7th to 9th grade level so that any adult can read it quickly and comfortably. My favorite scanners:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.readable.io&quot;&gt;Readable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hemingwayapp.com&quot;&gt;Hemingway App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A good ticket is not too big nor too small.&lt;/strong&gt; It suits the time-frame and team members involved in its execution. Think of an atom or a small molecule, not a rocket ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-bad-ticket&quot;&gt;A Bad Ticket&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
    table, th, td {
    border-collapse: collapse;
    border: 3px solid #bbdefe;
    padding: 5px;
    margin: 5px;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a ticket’s contents broken up into this form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;form field&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;field contents&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;summary&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Fix developer portal&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;reporter&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ryan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;date created&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2019-03-29&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;team&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Front End Team&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;current assignee&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;tbd&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;status&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;backlog&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;user story&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;acceptance criteria&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1. The fly-out panel on the left should work. Right now when I click it, nothing happens. When it opens, it obstructs my ability to interact with other controls on the page and this interferes with my workflow preferences. Then I can’t get it to close by clicking the X button.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Definition of Done&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;No bugs&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;attachments&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;work log&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;last modified by&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;last modified date&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few general problems with this ticket:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The summary is vague.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The reporter field may not give enough information to help readers contact the writer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Without background information, the Front End Team won’t really know why they’re doing what they’re asked to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acceptance criteria:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is vague and incomplete. It does not provide clear guidance about what is expected or required.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;jumbles multiple problems into one ticket.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The definition of done states only the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-good-ticket&quot;&gt;A Good Ticket&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at the same ticket reworked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;form field&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;field contents&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;summary&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Developer portal’s left flyout panel blocks underlying form&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;reporter&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ryan.haber@mycompany.com&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;date created&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2019-03-29&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;team&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Front End&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;current assignee&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;tbd&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;status&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;backlog&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;user story&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;As an external developer, I need to enter long key values in a form on MyCompany’s developer portal that I retrieve from a flyout panel in the same portal, but this panel covers the controls. So that I can work more accurately, I need to easily enter these values without having to jot them down on paper.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;acceptance criteria&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1. The panel helps developer-users capture and enter the values in some digital way. E.g.: “copy to clipboard” button or at least a copy-and-paste-able field to hold any values that might need to be recorded by the developer.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2. The interface makes valid workflow(s) intuitive.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3. Success is indicated by a 50%+ increase in the rate of form completion over 3 months.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Definition of Done&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1. Finished build asses all unit and integration.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2. Finished build accommodates at least 25 concurrent users.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3. Meets all standards set in MyCompany Base SLA.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;attachments&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;userFeedbackSurveySummary.xlsx&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;work log&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;last modified by&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;last modified date&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we see in this revised ticket?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The summary is clear and complete.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Readers will know who to contact with further questions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The user story provides background information that the development team needs to think of a good way to solve the problem.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ticket does not not attempt to micromanage the team, but does provide clear requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ticket has peeled off separate, albeit related, issues for other tickets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other useful information is attached that may help the team get a sense of what is frustrating users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you use this approach, you give the development team the information and freedom they need to make intelligent decisions to solve a problem rather than to act like cogs in a machine that needs constant managerial tinkering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion-coordinate---not-dominate&quot;&gt;Conclusion: Coordinate - Not Dominate&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You wouldn’t want an urban planner telling a civil engineer how to build a new bridge. The urban planner understands what is required, coordinates other moving parts, and makes this information available to the architects and engineers who then develop and implement a safe, economic, and beautiful design to enhance a city and serve its needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, it is not the role of a product manager, product owner, or business analyst to tell engineers how to do their job. Instead, these product management types should make clear what outcomes the stakeholders need and what constraints the business and its market impose on the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atomic unit of organization for the workflow that results is a ticket or issue. A good ticket serves as a point of reference for all involved. When they are well written, managers can arrange them into different to-do lists, epics, user story maps, or any other pattern they like. Managers can assess relative or even actual costs and values for development and then make sound decisions about organization priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That all starts with a good, clean ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/user-story/requirements/writing/2019/04/01/anatomy-of-a-good-ticket.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/user-story/requirements/writing/2019/04/01/anatomy-of-a-good-ticket.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>user-story</category>
        
        <category>requirements</category>
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Personal Thought Experiment</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When I was an undergraduate, a history major, I read a substantial amount. That’s what a history major at Loyola Univerity Maryland amounted to in the late 1990s: a reading, thinking, writing machine. I typically read and digested 200-300 pages per week for each of my seminars. I processed those assignments well enough to write about 10 pages in response to each of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then my life started to come into regular contact with the internet. Starting in 2007-10, I can see that my life was getting more and more “connected” to the Internet but less and less connected to the habit of sustained, deep reflection and thought. My social life hasn’t suffered. I spend as much time with people as ever and, thanks in part to the Internet, a wider range of acquaintances and friends than ever before both in person and remotely. But my time in contemplation and study has, since at least 2010, lets say, collapsed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That has to change. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My spiritual directors have always encouraged me to dig back into prayer and meditation. Now I’m also reading Cal Newton’s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/gp/product/1455586692/&quot;&gt;Deep Work: Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World&lt;/a&gt;. I’m increasingly convinced, convicted even, that I need to make a discipline of spending time in uninterrupted, disconnected study and contemplation of matters but spiritual and worldly. Here I will not go into the spiritual, but I do want to put out to the world this commitment. I hope that by doing so, my towering pride will force me to follow through lest I get teased and chided. Here’s the commitment, to go into effect the day I return home from my present business trip:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each weekday morning I will wake up 2 hours before the dog, at approximately 5:30 a.m.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each early morning, I will drink a glass of water, do some vigorous exercise, and then settle in for 90 minutes of reading and writing in an analog format: book or maybe a kindle or printouts, pen or pencil, and paper. No LCD screen. No Internet. No phone. I’ll transcribe anything worth sharing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I will spend this morning time in quiet without music, I’m thinking closed in my office where my desk is in the corner facing a wall.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then I will wake the lazy dog up and make him take a walk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of things I want to study:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new programming language (I think Julia, but tbd)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Product management and the business of software development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Personal finance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to do this for the end of October through the end of December, see how it goes, and see what are the fruits. I’ll report back here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this two month experiment, I’m also going to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scale back on social media in the way that I do every year at Lent: 1/2 hour on Sundays, blackout the rest of the week.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Block personal and work email checking to certain times of the day. I want to think through a schedule before committing to it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Block of web reading to a particular time of day, also TBD.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I’ll need to be in bed by 10:00 or so to have a real shot at making this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have to figure out what to do about instant messages (my office uses Slack) so that I can be available but also have fewer distractions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could use advice and suggestions, if you please. This is new ground for me. Or maybe it’s old ground for me, that’s gotten overgrown and gone to waste with tree-sized weeds and dense brush.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/hKU5dmGfSKY?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Radu Florin&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/search/photos/thinking?utm_source=unsplash&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_content=creditCopyText&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/career/philosophy/2018/10/08/a-personal-thought-experiment.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/career/philosophy/2018/10/08/a-personal-thought-experiment.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>career</category>
        
        <category>philosophy</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DeveloperHub.io - documentation made easy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;tl;dr&lt;/em&gt;: DeveloperHub.io (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.developerhub.io&quot;&gt;www.developerhub.io&lt;/a&gt;) is a new product that makes it easy to create documentation in minutes. It’s clean, has core features, and is headed in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-product&quot;&gt;the product:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeveloperHub.io is a new documentation product that clearly aims to get you writing and publishing quickly and easily. It succeeds. Within seconds of sitting down at the website, you’ll be creating instantly available documentation. With no need to build, convert, or template your docs, this is SaaS publishing at its easiest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/ryanhaber/productbrief/content/images/developerhub-wysiwyg.png&quot; alt=&quot;simple wysiwyg editor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeveloperHub.io has a simple and intuitive WYSIWYG editor, which means anybody can use it. Adding an image or a code block is as easy as a mouse click. The control panel is simple and reasonably intuitive. As a result, tasks like creating a new version from an existing version are also easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get basic white-labeling options: you can customize the color scheme, logo, and favicon. Obviously, this customization will not be enough for some enterprises. But for most of us looking to just get up and running, it’s plenty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also get some expected core features that would be required for any enterprise work, even for a small team: you can assign your own DNS to your documentation and you can set permissions for teammates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The output is clean and simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/ryanhaber/productbrief/content/images/developerhub-output-page.png&quot; alt=&quot;clean and simple output&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can play with the little mini docs demo I made: &lt;a href=&quot;https://api-ambassador.developerhub.io/v1.1/api-ambassador/getting-started&quot;&gt;API Ambassador Demo Docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-competition&quot;&gt;the competition:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeveloperHub.io is a turnkey SaaS docs portal for small-scale documentation projects. As indicated by the code block feature and, well, the name, this product clearly has an eye toward products that include code samples though it could be used easily for other small documentation projects. Other such products and services include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://clickhelp.com/&quot;&gt;ClickHelp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://paligo.net/&quot;&gt;Paligo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.proprofs.com/knowledgebase/&quot;&gt;ProProfs KnowledgeBase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These products are all SaaS docs portals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I distinguish DeveloperHub.io and its competition from products such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adobe.com/products/robohelp.html&quot;&gt;Adobe RoboHelp&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.madcapsoftware.com/products/flare/&quot;&gt;Madcap Flare&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oxygenxml.com/doc/versions/20.1/ug-editor/&quot;&gt;OxygenXML Editor&lt;/a&gt;. The key distinctions are platform, scale, and end product. DeveloperHub.io is SaaS, whereas these products are enterprise installations. DeveloperHub.io helps smaller documentation projects through their life cycle, while these products cope with thousands of documents across multiple projects – it’s overkill with too much overhead for smaller projects. DeveloperHub.io provides a live website as output. Those products support multiple export and output paths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some ways, Paligo is the closest: its UI is perhaps most similar to DeveloperHub.io’s. In reality, though, Paligo is an XML content authoring tool and probably more akin to OxygenXML for practical purposes. Paligo’s key value offering is single-source, multi-channel authoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DeveloperHub.io probably shouldn’t get into multi-channel output at this point. It’s for a developer audience mainly, and for that purpose can stick to the web and really dig into easy web docs authoring. Its team can really get into that fight by adding some single-source magic, which I propose here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;add-features&quot;&gt;add features:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make formatting controls a bit more obvious.&lt;/strong&gt; It’s probably me. The formatting controls weren’t obvious, but they are there. Once you figure them out or guess, they do make sense, so I’m not sure something better is really possible. Just something for the team to consider.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Snippets and variables for easy single-source writing.&lt;/strong&gt; Writers, like coders, often want to reuse blocks of content. Very often, they want to be able to edit these blocks in one place and have the edits mirrored in the other instances. We usually call thse blocks “snippets”. Variables allow users to insert values like current year that are updated at build or display time. Both snippets and variables are a common approach to keeping content fresh and consistent. For either snippets or variables, the team will need to pay careful attention to how styling is applied: whether from the source, the referring location, or some cascading approach.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal references.&lt;/strong&gt; It would be great to have hyperlinks within the documentation automatically updated in the event that a page’s URL or name changes.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swagger integration.&lt;/strong&gt; The dream here is a fancy and configurable UI for OpenAPI/Swagger documentation built into the product. The API reference could be a stand-alone page or it could be inserted into existing docs. The ability to directly edit the HTML of a page would provide a short-term or less-dreamy approach to this enhancement.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional customizations.&lt;/strong&gt; Some clients will want a landing page that they can more fully or totally control. Generally speaking, it will also be useful to allow an HTML view of any particular content page as well, though probably within the existing template. Writers may want this view so they can code tables, set internal anchors, etc. The ability to inject CSS and JavaScript may also be helpful to many users.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;monetize-it&quot;&gt;monetize it:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a basic tier of free use with the product scaling along with customers’ needs and ability to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The DeveloperHub.io team could charge for: additional users, additional customizations, additional plugins, and bulk import/export or maybe import/export at a data level.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Add a service to supply and charge for: an embeddable HTML element with supporting CSS/JavaScript that does a quick, autocomplete/suggested-completion query of the documentation. Content developers can embed such an element in, among other places, customer support request pages.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;scale-it&quot;&gt;scale it:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get the word out at technical writing trade shows, associations, and forums.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/brief/docs-tools/2018/07/22/developer-hub.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/brief/docs-tools/2018/07/22/developer-hub.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>brief</category>
        
        <category>docs-tools</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Things Clear</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across this list in Forbes and really like it a lot. It matches my experience very well and has got me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the list: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www3.forbes.com/leadership/ten-reasons-successful-people-change-jobs-more-often/&quot;&gt;Forbes’s 10 Reasons Successful People Change Jobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for my thoughts, building off the list from Forbes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list closely represents my experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From 2009 to 2015, I doubled and then tripled my salary and gained a host of marketable skills and even some expertise by changing jobs enough to raise the eyebrows of every stability-minded person who knows and loves me. During those years, I had four full-time employers and also spent time freelancing. Grandmaternal eyebrow-raising has definitely accompanied my journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/ryanhaber/productbrief/content/images/ladder.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing. If you see a career as climbing a corporate ladder, you may be making a mistake. Corporations aren’t really ladders with a single path and a line of people all steadily advancing each in their turn. Really, corporations are more like pyramids with lots of workers, fewer middle managers, even fewer executives, and a single owner or board or CEO or whoever sits atop the whole thing at your company. And the point is that unless the corporation is growing rapidly, someone usually has to die, retire, or leave for a job above you for the position to open up. Taking for granting that the only way to advance your career is to climb the pyramid implies that you only go forward by growing from doing work to managing people who do work. That’s not true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/ryanhaber/productbrief/content/images/lillypads.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t just see the corporation where I work. I see the whole labor market for my industry, my profession, and for related industries and professions. I see them all as forming a big pond with lilypads and stones and islands. I step from rock to shallow spot as useful or necessary and I always have all kinds of directions open to me. More more stability-minded friends are amazed or amused, but it doesn’t even give pause to the recruiters who track me down on a regular basis asking if I’d like to make a change. (I love my current employer, am learning tons, and have lots so of potential for career growth without shifting jobs, so I’m probably not looking to shift at the moment, but you can always ask.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for changing positions frequently:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Employers big and small lay off employees when they cannot afford to pay for or have no use for the employees’ work anymore. It makes sense for employees to change employers when we have no use for or can do better than the employer’s work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Employers big and small lay off employees regularly when they think they can find someone to do the same work for less. It makes sense for workers to leave employers when we think we can get paid more to do the same work elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Employers big or small eventually sack employees who are fractious and unpleasant to work with. It makes sense to leave a toxic employer rather than suck it up.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, it’s a false feeling that large employers provide more stability than small ones, even if stability’s your thing. Large companies buy out, get bought out, go bankrupt, lay off workers to keep up the bottom line, and all the rest of it, all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a relatively simple thing: sometimes you really have learned all you are going to learn at a job. Sometimes you really can get more money for the same work, and you know because you see the job listings or because recruiters approach you and tell you. Sometimes you find yourself working three months in a toxic environment and the idea of “sticking it out” for another three or four years (so you look stable) is miserable. To me, these are all signs that it’s time to split. Split gracefully, by all means, burning no bridges if can be managed, and waiting until something better is lined up if at all possible. But still: go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Valuing stability is fine. Stable communities are good, and stability in family life is key. I have a few friends that have been my friends for thirty or more years. But if you make stability paramount in your career, though, don’t be surprised if you stagnate in your career. Stagnation is what happens when living things become too stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some professions, like teaching, in which stability really is valued and there isn’t really a career ladder or pyramid or whatever if you want to continue teaching, my experience probably doesn’t match up well with yours. But in my industry (software development) and in others that value dynamism, like defense industries, finance, marketing, creative/design work, and more, I think you probably find many experiences that corroborate mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just my $0.02, for what it’s worth, though I have to admit that I’m glad Mr. Forbes agrees with me. He seems to have done OK.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/career/2017/07/22/making-things-clear.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/career/2017/07/22/making-things-clear.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>career</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>I Never Meant to Be a Technical Writer</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I never meant to be a technical writer, or whatever it is that I now do for a living. Whatever it is, I really like it, though. My career has had its ups and downs, and if there is such a thing as a normal career, mine is not it. Probably the most un-normal thing about my career, though, is how it got started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My career started over a jelly doughnut. After leaving the seminary where I had spent a few years studying for the Catholic priesthood, I went on a brief vacation to Europe to unwind. When I returned, I had to get about the business of finding a job. Or something. I hadn’t even really begun yet when there I was, standing around in my parish’s hall eating the jelly doughnut. A man I knew, Paul, came up and started chatting me up. “How’s your transition going?” “Went to Europe, did you? How was that?” Answering the questions and keeping up conversation was made challenging because my jelly doughnut was beginning to ooze like a puppy poking its nose through a gap between a door and the jamb. “You have work yet?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Um, well, not just yet.” A blob of jelly escaped its confines and plopped onto my shoe. I played it off, but Paul glanced down at my shoe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, what can you do?” Paul asked. The answer to this question was vaguer than you’d expect unless you know that my only university degree is a bachelor of arts from a liberal arts college. I studied history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, I can study,” I said unconvincingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Study? That’s good,” Paul responded, unconvinced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Research. I learn quickly.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I see.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, as an afterthought, I added, “I can write.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this, Paul’s eyes lit up. “You can write?” he repeated. His hushed tone was more appropriate to a great discovery: “You found gold?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You mean English, right?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes, English. You can write English?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Um, yes. Can’t everybody?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul chuckled. “Heh. Not where I work, man. Say, listen, what are you doing Monday?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was caught up on the bit about English, so it took me a second to respond, and when I did, my response, “Well, I’m not working,” sounded a bit more petulant than was quite right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Why don’t you come into my office? I think we’re trying to hire a technical writer. Very difficult to find a good one, you know. Why don’t you come in, look around, and you can talk with the right people there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by the thought of eating and getting my own place to stay. Still, there was this nagging concern. Had he said “technical writer”? I thought I’d been pretty clear that English was my thing. Not technical. Whatever that would mean. Still, food is food, and worth a shot. “Um, sure. So, um, technical writing?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah. Technical writing. You think you can do it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’re still talking about English, right?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yes. Well, computer software. In English.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah,” I said, about as convincingly as I sounded when I told him that I could study. “For sure.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Great,” he said. He gave me his card with the office’s address and then, looking around nervously, said to nobody in particular, “I think one of my kids is setting fire to something or poking somebody. I’d better…” and he went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;https://s3.amazonaws.com/ryanhaber/productbrief/content/images/microsoft-manual-of-style-original-imadaqnxubcthhtg.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width:300px;margin-right: auto; margin-left: auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I turned on my heel, returned to my sister and brother-in-law’s where I was staying, temporarily I hoped, and started looking around on his bookshelves. This all happened when books were still a thing but were becoming a not-a-thing, at least in my industry. My brother-in-law works in IT, and I thought I had seen a dull-looking but suddenly relevant book on his shelf. And there it was: the Microsoft Manual of Style. Also present were a number of user manuals to various software applications. I spent the rest of the day studying their style and trying to figure out what technical writing might mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Monday came around, I went into the office at the address that Paul had given me. The receptionist showed me to Paul, and Paul brought me to a room with a computer. A man about my age, an engineer as it turned out, joined us and began to walk me through a software suite as Paul narrated very eagerly, very proudly. The software had a clunky user interface that masked something really cool: software for managing multiple security appliances of varying types, makes, and models in a single platform. It doesn’t sound revolutionary, but when network video recorders were just coming onto the scene, it was pretty new stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“What do you need me to write, Paul?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, anything, really.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Anything?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Yeah, we don’t have any documentation yet. Pick something that needs documenting, and document it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So document I did. I found a spot of the interface that looked particularly unwieldy apparently intended to complicate a task that could have been simple and was certainly important. I wrote up a set of step-by-step instructions for “Doing Such-and-Such.” I took great care to clearly call out informational notes separate from the various steps to be done. When I’d finished, I showed my work to Paul. “Very good. Very clear. Except…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Except?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Can you add more pictures?” he asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t expected pictures. I could do pictures. After fiddling with the print screen button, I added some pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Beautiful. You’re hired.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that’s how I got started technical writing. How I got to where I am is another installment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Life Skills Takeaway&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most new jobs are made by small businesses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Small businesses are more likely than large businesses to hire someone based on potential as much as on experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/career/2017/06/17/i-never-meant-to-be-a-technical-writer.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/career/2017/06/17/i-never-meant-to-be-a-technical-writer.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>career</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Resources to Learn Tech Writing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am frequently asked, “What are some good places to learn technical writing?” This page will be an evolving document listing off forums, organizations, and even books (gasp!) that have helped me improve my game. I may include some that look excellent even if they haven’t been pivotal in my particular career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;books-and-online-guides&quot;&gt;Books and Online Guides&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;english-and-tech-comms-usage&quot;&gt;English and Tech Comms Usage&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chicagomanualofstyle.org/home.html&quot;&gt;Chicago Manual of Style&lt;/a&gt; online, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Chicago-Manual-Style-16th/dp/0226104206&quot;&gt;buy a copy&lt;/a&gt; to settle all questions about grammar and usage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Elements-Style-Fourth-William-Strunk/dp/020530902X/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1497131988&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=elements+of+style+strunk+and+white&quot;&gt;The Elements of Style&lt;/a&gt;, because it’s inexpensive, brief, and an excellent guide to how to write clean and simple prose. If you haven’t read it, you probably stink at writing. Just kidding. Kind of.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Complete-Plain-Words-Ernest-Gowers/dp/1567922031/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1497132032&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=complete+plain+words&quot;&gt;The Complete Plain Words&lt;/a&gt;, basically a longer form of &lt;em&gt;The Elements of Style&lt;/em&gt; and - I’m not joking - good for daily reading. It teaches more about a mentality than about memorizing rules.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Point-Dictionary-Concise-Writing/dp/0393347176/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1497132167&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=to+the+point+a+dictionary+of+concise+writing&quot;&gt;To The Point: A Dictionary of Concise Writing&lt;/a&gt;. You look up a phrase and this nifty book provides a briefer alternative. I use it when I am sensing my inner poet taking control of my tech comms work. The more you use it, the less you need to.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Microsoft-Manual-Style-4th-Corporation/dp/0735648719/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1497131810&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=microsoft+manual+of+style+5th+edition&quot;&gt;Microsoft Manual of Style&lt;/a&gt; for all language more specific to software documentation as well as formatting usage.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;feedback-on-your-writing&quot;&gt;Feedback on Your Writing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hemingwayapp.com/&quot;&gt;Hemingway App&lt;/a&gt; is geared toward improving your writing. Generally, it seems to score with an eye toward helping you write very clean, active prose more or less suitable for tech writing. It gives lots of generally good advice about writing good, clean prose.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/content/images/2017/06/logo.io.png&quot;&gt;Readable.io&lt;/a&gt; evaluates text giving you a variety of scores based on different academic scales that I don’t understand. But what I do understand is the simple letter grade that it gives. It also gives you some statistical feedback, such as the percentage of your words that are adverbs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-craft-of-tech-comms&quot;&gt;The Craft of Tech Comms&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://smile.amazon.com/Developing-Quality-Technical-Information-Handbook/dp/0133118975/ref=mt_paperback?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;me=&quot;&gt;Developing Quality Technical Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01A2QL9SS/ref=kinw_myk_ro_title&quot;&gt;Modern Technical Writing&lt;/a&gt; focuses on software documentation and is a gem of a book.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ben1962hummel.files.wordpress.com/2017/04/white_paper-the_definitive_guide_to_creating_api_documentation.pdf&quot;&gt;The Definitive Guide to
Creating API Documentation&lt;/a&gt; by the folks from Madcap Flare, an industry standard for technical writing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;organizations&quot;&gt;Organizations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stc.org/&quot;&gt;Society for Technical Communications&lt;/a&gt; is a real-life organization to help tech comms people network and improve our craft. The society produces salary guides, a peer-reviewed journal as well as an online magazine, and lots of activities and an annual conference. Disclaimer: I’m a member. Warning: it’s not cheap. Advice: I do find it worthwhile or I wouldn’t keep renewing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.writethedocs.org&quot;&gt;Write the Docs&lt;/a&gt; From their website: “Write the Docs is a series of conferences and local meetups focused on all things related to software documentation… We consider everyone who cares about communication, documentation, and their users to be a member of our community. This can be programmers, tech writers, developer advocates, customer support, marketers, and anyone else who wants people to have great experiences with software.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/InfoDevDC/&quot;&gt;InfoDevDC&lt;/a&gt; is a nifty meetup in Northern Virgina. Disclaimer: I co-run the thing. Advice: It’s still pretty darn nifty.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;forums-online&quot;&gt;Forums Online&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/3709151&quot;&gt;LinkedIn - API Docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/112571&quot;&gt;LinkedIn - Technical Writer Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/technicalwriting/&quot;&gt;Reddit - Technical Writing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://productbrief.github.io/writing/2017/06/10/resources-to-learn-tech-writing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://productbrief.github.io/writing/2017/06/10/resources-to-learn-tech-writing.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>writing</category>
        
      </item>
    

  </channel>
</rss>
